Harvey Pitkin Papers 1884-1968 Mss.Ms.Coll.78
American Philosophical Society
- Series II. Yuki Materials, 1900-1968; 7.25 linear feet (Box Series II: 3-8)
  - Series II-A. Research notes, 1900-1960; 48 folders (Box Series IIA: 3-4)
    - Monosyllabic noun stems: TU 39-44, 1931-1932, 1958?; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
      Annotations by Kroeber. "TU" seems to indicate Typed Uldall.
      See also: Ser. II-A. Uldall, Hans, Verb stems, stem tones, and suffixes.
      See also: Ser. II-A. Uldall, Hans, Monosyllabic noun stems U 10-16.
    - Monosyllabic noun stems: U 10-16, 1931-1932, 1957; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
      Annotated by Kroeber.
      See also: Ser. II-A. Uldall, Hans, Monosyllabic noun stems: TU 39-44.
    - Verb stems, stem tones, and suffixes: U 17-23, 46, 75; V 1, 1931, 1957-1958?; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 12.
    - Verbs: W 5-23, 25-30, 1931-1932, 1958; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
    - Verbs: 31-50, 1932; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 13.
    - Yuki language -- notes, 1932?; Photocopy; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
    - Yuki tones: T 1-14, 1932, 1957; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIA-4)
  - Series II-B. Vocabularies and slip files, 1903-1958; 36 folders, 6 boxes (Box Series IIB: 4-7)
    Includes a Coast Yuki word list recorded by Harold Driver, 1935, and photocopies of John P. Harrington's English-Yuki slipfile. Among files containing material by Kroeber are ones containing a word list of animal names; miscellaneous Huchnom slips; a list containing Wappo, Yuki, Coast Yuki, and Huchnom words for man, woman, and person; a Wappe-Yuki comparison (1903, 1908); and Yuki and Huchnom word lists. The unfiled slips from the Kroeber-Uldall Yuki morpheme slip file are housed in folders; otehrwise the slipfile (ca.1958) is organized by Yuki morpheme, with separate (additional) slips for suffixes and dialects. One section is marked "Old orthography." An english-Wappo slip file is based on Radin's notes.
    - Coast Yuki word list, 1935; Photocopy; Driver, Harold (Box Series IIB-4)
      KFI: Dr.1, item 22 (5).
    - English-Yuki slipfile, n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB: 4-7)
      - Folder 1, "A", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-4)
      - Folder 2, "Ba-Bo", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-4)
      - Folder 3, "Br-Bu", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 4, "C", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 5, "D", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 6, "E", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 7, "F", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 8, "G", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 9, "H", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 10, "I-J", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 11, "K", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-5)
      - Folder 12, "L", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 13, "M", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 14, "N", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 15, "O", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 16, "P-Q", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 17, "R", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 18, "Sa-Sl", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 19, "Sm-Sw", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 20, "Ta-Th", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-6)
      - Folder 21, "Ti-V", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-7)
      - Folder 22, "Wa-Whe", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-7)
      - Folder 23, "Whi-Y", n.d.; Harrington, John Peabody (Box Series IIB-7)
    - Animal names word list, n.d.; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIB-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 7.
    - Huchnom slips, n.d.; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIB-7)
    - List of Wappo, Huchnom, Yuki, and Coast Yuki words for person, man, and woman, Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIB-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 22 (3a).
    - Wappo-Yuki comparison, 1903, 1908; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIB-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 2b.
    - Yuki and Huchnom word lists, Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIB-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 6c.
    - Yuki morhpemes slip file, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB-7)
      - -P to -Pis, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB-7)
      - -Poy, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB-7)
      - Suffixes -S to -Suy, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB-7)
      - U 56-57, W 50, 1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB-7)
        KFI: Dr. 1, item 20, unfiled slips.
    - Yuki phonetic transcriptions list, n.d.; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIB-7)
    - Yuki Š stem dictionary: Š verbs, nouns, and adverbs, 1957?; Pitkin, Harvey (Box Series IIB-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 22 (4).
    - Yuki and Huchnom vocabularies, 1907 (Box Series IIB-7)
      "Redwood Valley R./Used in ethnogeography of Pomo".
    - Yuki morphemes slipfile, ca.1958; ca.12,850 slips; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 1-6)
      - a-i, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 1)
      - k-m, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 2)
      - n-t', ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 3)
      - č-y, suffixes -Am to -ki, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 4)
      - Suffixes -kil to -yAu n, ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 5)
      - Dialects and suffices (unfiled slips), ca.1958; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 6)
    - Yuki vocabulary slips (old orthography), ca.1958; ca.255 slips; Kroeber, A. L. and Hans Uldall (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 1)
      Filed in Ser. II-B, Yuki morpheme slipfile box 1
    - English index to Wappo slips ex. Radin, ca.1,745 slips; [Radin, Paul]? (Box Series IIB - Slipfile 6)
      Filed in Ser. II-B, Yuki morpheme slipfile box 6
  - Series II-C. Texts and manuscripts, 1901-1958; 18 folders (Box Series IIC-7)
    Manuscripts and texts relating to the Yuki language by Kroeber, working primarily with consultant Ralph Moore, as well as information on Moore's ancestry and dialect. The texts include both transcriptions and translations of seven Yuki tales or songs, and the originals notes for tehse are cross-referenced in the Kroeber notebooks in Series II-A. The songs are of adolescence, thunder twins, coyote, coyote and crow, coyote and wildcat, taikomol, and feather dance. There is a Huchnom creation story, translated by Robert Lowie, Pitkin's transcriptions and translations of of the wildcat and coyote, and untitled Yuki text, North wind and Sun, Coyote and Crow, the Coast Yui, and Wildcat, taken from Hans Uldall's notes.
    The series also includes Uldall's "Preliminary Report on Yuki Tones," with additional notes by Kroeber; Uldall's Yuki texts (on which Pitkin worked), which include those listed above, as well as Northwind and Sun, Wildcat and Coyote, The Coast Yuki, Coyote and Crow, Wildcat, Coyote and Crow Cycle, and Coyote and Skunk.
    - History of the recording of Yuki, 1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
      Also titled: "History of Yuki language study".
    - Ralph Moore: Ancestry and dialect, 1931-1932, 1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Significances of some of Uldall's orthographies, 1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Yuki connectives, 1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Yuki language and phonetics, Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Yuki texts -- transcriptions, 1902; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
      - Adolescence, 1902; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
        KFI: Dr. 1, item 14.
        See Ser. II-A. Kroeber, A. L., Yuki notebook 32 for translation.
      - "Ā nā' mo'l-nA n mū' sp-nA" [Thunder twins], 1901; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
        See Ser. II-A. Kroeber, A. L., Yuki notebook 20 for translation.
      - Coyote, 1902; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
        See Ser. II-A. Kroeber, A. L., Yuki notebook 29 for translation.
      - Coyote and crow, 1902; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
      - Coyote and wildcat, 1902; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
        See Ser. II-A. Kroeber, A. L., Yuki notebook 27 for translation.
      - "hīl ā tAt ya' t' ei ei taikô' mol", 1902; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
        See Ser. II-A. Kroeber, A. L., Yuki notebook 27or translation.
      - "KôpA' wô' klami" [Feather dance], 1901; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Huchnom creation myth -- translation, 1917; Lowie, Robert Harry, 1883-1957 (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Wildcat and coyote -- Phonetic transcription and partial translation, 1957; Pitkin, Harvey (Box Series IIC-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 20c.
      "Original phonetic transcription from tape of Wildcat and Coyote (version variant of Kroeber and Uldall recordings)."
    - Wildcat and Coyote text -- transcription in Yuki, 1957; Pitkin, Harvey (Box Series IIC-7)
    - Yuki texts from uldall folder pages VIB and following -- transcription and translation, 1958; Pitkin, Harvey (Box Series IIC-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 20d and 20f.
      Texts transcribed: Untitled, Northwind and sun, Coyote and Crow, The Coast Yuki, and Wildcat.
      See related: Ser. II-C, Uldall, Hans, yuki texts.
    - Preliminary report on Yuki tones, with notes to Uldall essay by A. L. Kroeber, 1932, 1958; Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIC-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5d.
      See also Ser. II-A. Krober, A. L. and Dell Hymes, [Comments on...]"
      See also: Call no. 497.3 B63c Yk.1 for another edited copy of this work.
    - Yuki texts -- transcriptions and translations, Uldall, Hans (Box Series IIC-7)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 20g.
      Northwind and sun
      Wildcat and Coyote
      Coast Yuki
      Coyote and Crow
      Wildcat
      Coyote and Crow cycle
      Coyote and Skunk
      See also: Ser. II-C. Pitkin, Harvey, "Yuki text from Uldall folder..."
  - Series II-D. Phonetic tracings, 1912-1958; 19 folders (Box Series IID-8)
    Phonetic tracings, esp. kymograms, of Yuki words as recorded from Ralph Moore. For more information on their recording see Kroeber's article in Scientific American.
    - Disyllables: Huùtle -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint and orig. (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 14 graphs.
    - Disyllables, polysyllables -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 13 graphs.
    - Final glide-vowel -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 3 graphs.
    - Final glottal stops, breaths, w/y devoiced, sonorants -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 11 graphs.
    - Final sonorant -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 5 graphs.
    - Final sonorants -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
    - Final stops: aspirate, glottal -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 7 graphs.
    - Final vowel: a a -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 9 graphs.
    - Glottal stop -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
    - Glottal stop in vowel -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
    - Initial vowel: u only -- Kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 2 graphs.
    - Index of words traced on kymograph, 1912, 1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a.
    - Phonetics notes and list of words traced, 1923; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5f.
    - Miscellaneous tracings -- kymograms, n.d.; Photoprint and orig. (Oversize 1 / Series IID)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5c.
      - Folder 1: unlabeled, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-1)
      - Folder 2: unlabeled, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-2)
      - Folder 3: 19-27 breath onlty, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-3)
      - Folder 4: 40, 41, 52-56, breath only, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-4)
      - Folder 5: 30-39 wildcat test[?]. A-Ø as marked in printed book. Breath only., n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-5)
      - Folder 6: Breath only -- fast, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-6)
      - Folder 7: XXIX, L, LI, LII Nose only, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-7)
      - Folder 8: Tamb[?], n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-8)
      - Folder 9: Nose only 46, 47, n.d. (Oversize 1, Folder Series IID-9)
    - Mounted black on white tracings -- kymograms, 1912, 1958 (Box Series IID-8)
    - Palatograms and word list, 1923 (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 30 color pencil sketches showing word pronouncation on the tongue.
    - Selected and analyzed tracings -- kymograms, 1912, 1958 (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 15 graphs.
    - Stop V stop -- kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprints (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 12 graphs.
    - Tracings not used in 1958 -- kymograms, 1912 (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5b. Image note: 18 graphs.
    - Tracings to be contact-printed -- kymograms, 1912, 1958 (Box Series IID-8)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 25 graphs.
    - Unidentified tracings -- kymograms, n.d.8 (Oversize 1 / Series IID)
  - Series II-E. Correspondence, 1932-1968; 3 folders (Box Series IIE-8)
    Includes an index by Kroeber to his correspondence with the linguist Hans Uldall, and Yuki consultant Ralph Moore, as well as Kroeber's correspondence with Uldall and Theodora Kroeber's correspondence with Piktin.
    - Correspondence with Louis Hjelmslev and Hans Uldall, 1932-1933, 1957-1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIE-8)
      KFI Dr. 1, item 22.
    - List of correspondence with Hans Uldall and Ralph Moore, 1923-1933, 1958; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIE-8)
      KFI Dr. 1, item 19.
    - Correspondence with Harvey Pitkin, 1968; Kroeber, Theodora (Box Series IIE-8)
- Series III. Miscellaneous Materials, 1904-1958; 1.25 linear feet (Box Series III: 9-10)
  Assorted materials on a variety of languages, including Yahi, Hamawi, Achumawi, Maidu, Cherokee, Mohave, Kato, Chumash, Luiseno, and Kwakiutl. The Yahi material was collected from Ishi between 1911 and 1915. This series follows the same general arrangement as the preceding series.
  - Series III-A. Research notes, 1904-1956; 8 folders (Box Series IIIA-9)
    Notes arranged alphabetically by author or recorder, and then alphabetically by title. Five notebooks contain texts collected by A. M. Halpern of "Fox and Coyote," oral histories of spiritual power and doctors, Hat Creek, creation myths, and the political history of the Hawai and Achumawi. Two of the notebooks concern the Maidu and Cherokee. T.T. Waterman's notebook contains information obtained from the Yahi consultant Ishi through the interpreter Sam Batwi.
    - Linguistic notes, 1936; Halpern, A. M. (Box Series IIIA-9)
      - Adin [Hill, Hamawi, Achumawi] notebook, 1936?; Halpern, A. M. (Box Series IIIA-9)
      - Alturas I [Hamawi, Achumawi] notebook, 1936?; Halpern, A. M. (Box Series IIIA-9)
      - Alturas II [Hamawi, Achumawi] notebook, 1936?; Halpern, A. M. (Box Series IIIA-9)
      - Auburn, Sugar Pine Hill, Maidu notebook, 1936?; Halpern, A. M. (Box Series IIIA-9)
      - Cherokee [Maidu] notebook, 1936?; Halpern, A. M. (Box Series IIIA-9)
    - [Bibliography of] Malayo-Polynesian languages -- Notes, n.d.; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIA-9)
    - Mohave disposition and description -- notes, 1904, [1956?]; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIA-9)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 16.
    - Southern Yana, Yahi notebook, 1911; Waterman, T. T., (Thomas Talbot), 1885- (Box Series IIIA-9)
      Recorded from Ishi.
  - Series III-B. Vocabularies and slip files, 1912-1953; 7 folders, 1 box (Box Series IIIB: 9-10)
    The series contains four items: a list of Chumash geographical terms and Kato word list by Kroeber; a blank vocabulary and/or phonetic workform; a slip file of Kwakiutl names created by Franz Boas and others. The Kwakiutl names were taken from three sources: a manuscript(s) by George Hunt; Boas' "Contributions to the ethnology of the Kwakiutl" Columbia University Contributions to Anthropology vol. 3 (1925); and Boas' "The religion of the Kwakiutl Indians" Columbia University Contributions to Anthropology vol. 10 (1930). The slipfile is arranged into personal names, myth names, tribe and and clan names, with some unsorted slips.
    - Kwakiutl slipfile: personal names, myth names, tribe and clan names, ca.2,375 slips; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942, et al. (Box Series IIIB - Kwakiutl Slipfile 1)
    - Chumash geographical terms -- Notes, 1912, 1953; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIB-9)
    - Kato word list -- Notes, 1912, 1953; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIB-9)
    - Luiseno adjectives derived from nouns -- slipfile, n.d.; 2 folders; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIB-9)
    - Luiseno verb stems -- slipfile, n.d.; 2 folders; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIB-10)
    - Vocabulary and phonetic workform (Box Series IIIB-10)
  - Series III-C. Texts and manuscripts, 1914-1956; 3 folders (Box Series IIIC-10)
    Manuscripts and texts relating to Kwakiutl, Luiseno, and Yahi. These include an annotated page proof for a portion of Edward S. Curtis' The North American Indian (Plimpton Press, 1907-1930) concerning the Kwakiutl potlatch (with annotations by Krober); Kroeber's notes on English verb classification and Luiseno verbs; and a photocopy of portions of Kroeber's notebooks identifying and mapping Yahi place names recorded from Ishi in 1914.
    - "Kwakiutl potlatch," from The North American Indian (Northwood, Mass.: Plimpton Press), 137-155, Page proofs; Curtis, Edward S. (Box Series IIIC-10)
      Annotations by Kroeber, "File under Myers."
    - English verb classification; and Luiseno verbs which focus on a sensory aspect of a movement or act, 1956?; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIC-10)
    - Yahi place names, 1914; Photocopy; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960 (Box Series IIIC-10)
      Ishi. Pp.68a-c, 69-81, 95-103, 105-115; maps
  - Series III-D. Phonetic tracings, 1911-1958; 2 folders (Box Series IIID-10)
    Phonetic tracings (kymograms) of Yahi words as recorded from Ishi.
    - English tracings: Bake, bad, pick, tag -- kymograms, 1912, 1958; Photoprint and orig. (Box Series IIID-10)
      KFI: Dr. 1, item 5a. Image note: 4 graphs.
    - Yahi phonetic tracings -- kymograms, 1912, 1958 (Box Series IIID-10)
      Ishi. Image note: 13 graphs.
  - Series III-E. Other correspondence, 1961 (Box Series IIIE-10)
    Correspondence between Mary Haas, Dell Hymes, and Harvery Pitkin regarding the use, transfer, and housing of linguistic materials at the Departments of Linguistics and Anthropology at the University of California.
    - University of California, Berkeley. Department of Lingusitics, 1961 (Box Series IIIE-10)
      Correspondence of Mary R. Haas, Dell Hymes, Harvey Pitkin.